原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/yNEWkY9D2k4
原视频发布日期：20200623
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
你好 我是Scott Manley
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
最近载人龙飞船发射到了国际空间站
The recent launch of the Dragon to the International Space Station
意味着这是九年来的第一次
meant that this was the first time in nine years
乘员通过国际空间站美国部分的对接口进入了空间站
that crew have boarded the station through the docking ports in the US section of the station.
还有不少人问我 为什么美国舱段的对接适配器的布局是这样的？
And a number of you have asked me why the docking adapters in the US station are laid out the way they are.
特别是为什么加压的对接适配器会设计成这种奇怪的偏移？
In particular why are the pressurized mating adapters designed with this weird offset
这意味着宇航员必须在这个危险的角落里通过
in the axis that means that astronauts have to negotiate this dangerous corner
这显然增加了 撞到你的头的机会
which obviously increases the chance of banging your head.
所以这条通道是一个叫加压对接适配器(PMA)的部件的一部分
so this tunnel is part of a component called the pressurized mating adapter.
在一端和另一端之间有一个28英寸或71厘米的偏移
And between one end and the other there is a 28 inch or 71 centimeter offset.
加压对接适配器的工作是转接两个不同的对接适配器 并在中间加一个加压通道
The pressurized mating adapters job is to adapt a pressurized tunnel between two different docking adapters.
空间站是一个国际项目
The space station is an international project
其起源于美国自由号空间站和俄罗斯和平2空间站
which has its roots in the US Space Station Freedom and the Russian Mir 2 Station.
而不同的舱段之间也有多种不同的对接和停泊标准在使用
And there are multiple different docking and berthing standards in use between the different segments.
俄罗斯部分的空间站是使用联盟号杆-锥式对接机构对接在一起的
The Russian side of the station was docked together using the Soyuz probe-and-drogue style docking mechanism.
其实俄罗斯段上使用的有两种变体
And there's actually two variants of this used on the Russian segment.
有一种是老式的 也就是联盟号和进步号使用的款式
There's the old-style Soyuz and Progress design
它的外侧有一个硬对接环 有八个锁扣
which has an outer hard docking ring with eight latches.
还有一些较新的被称为混合式设计的
And then there's some newer ones which are called the hybrid design
那些有12个锁扣 被用于大型模块
and those have 12 latches and those are used for the larger modules.
空间站的国际部分
The International side of the space station
是使用大型通用停泊机构(CBM)转接器固定在一起的
is held together by using the large common berthing mechanism adapters.
而当你看到空间站内部的方形舱门时
And when you see the square hatches on the interior of the station
那就是用CBM将两个模块用螺栓固定在一起
that's when two modules have been bolted together using the CBMs.
现在CBM不适合进行自由飞行对接机动
Now the CBM isn't suitable for free-flying docking maneuvers.
它需要用操纵臂抓住其中一个模块
It requires that one of the modules be grabbed by a manipulator arm.
然后小心翼翼的放在合适的位置接触 然后慢慢的对接 最后用螺栓固定在一起
And then carefully placed in contact in the right location and slowly mated and bolted together.
较大的对接系统其实存在着热膨胀的问题
Larger docking systems actually have problems with thermal expansion
所以这个过程是故意放慢的 以确保双方达到平衡 并正确对接
so the process is intentionally slow to make sure that both sides reach equilibrium and line up correctly.
最后就是双性外围连接系统(APAS)
And finally there's the androgynous peripheral attachment system.
而这是俄罗斯设计的对接接口
And that is a Russian designed docking interface
并用于空间站的俄罗斯和国际部分之间的对接
and is used between the Russian and international sections of the space station.
而航天飞机与空间站的对接也采用了同样的设计
And the same design is also used to dock the space shuttle to the space station.
所以双性这个词
So the word androgynous
应该是标志着设计上两边的连接没有差别
is supposed to signify the design has no differences between either side of the connections.
所以理论上任何有APAS的航天器都可以对接在一起
So in theory any vessels with APAS could dock together.
理论上是这样 实际操作上就不太一样了
In theory not so much in practice.
还有就是最新的国际对接系统标准(IDSS)
And then there's also the newer international docking system standard
这是一个不兼容的APAS的演变 这就是龙飞船 星际客机和猎户座正在使用
which is an incompatible evolution of APAS and that's what Dragon Starliner and Orion are using.
那么(回到)我们所说的这个斜面部分叫做PMA
So this slanted section that we're talking about is called pressurized mating adapter.
一边连接到CBM
On one side it connects to the common berthing mechanism
并在另一侧连接到APAS
and on the other side it connects to APAS.
国际空间站有三台这样的设备
There are three of these in the station.
其中有两个是已经安装到团结号舱段上发射的
Two of them were launched already installed to the Unity module
后面的PMA-1与俄罗斯的曙光号舱段连接
with PMA-1 at the back connecting to the Russian Zarya module
而前面的PMA-2最初是用来对接航天飞机的
and PMA-2 in the front initially being used to dock the space shuttle.
随着空间站的扩大 PMA-2被移来移去 以便增加新的舱段
As the station was expanded, PMA-2 was moved about to allow new modules to be added
而它目前位于和谐号舱段的前部
and it currently sits on the front of the Harmony module.
还有第三个PMA 航天飞机只用过几次
There is a third pressurized mating adapter which was only used by the shuttle a couple of times
而实际上它一生中的大部分时间都在被用作储物柜
and has actually spent most of his life being used as a storage closet.
但它最终会证明它的用途
But it will finally prove its use
当国际空间站可能需要多个商业航天器同时与空间站对接时
when the ISS may need to have multiple commercial spacecraft docked to the space stations simultaneously.
由于PMA-1是一个永久性的固定设施
Since PMA-1 is a permanent fixture.
它不仅仅是各段之间的通道
It's not just a passageway between the segments.
实际上它还被用于大量的存储
It's actually also used for a lot of storage.
而它墙壁上布满了货物转运袋
With the walls being covered in cargo transfer bags
这些袋子里包含毛巾 湿巾和橡胶手套等通用物品
containing generic items like towels, wet wipes and rubber gloves.
为了准备迎接新的商业载人飞船
In preparation for the new commercials crew spacecraft,
两个外部PMA进行了改装 增加了一个国际对接适配器(IDA)
the two external PMA's were modified with the addition of an international docking adaptor
这能将APAS标准转换为新的IDSS
which then converted the APAS standard to the new international docking standard.
那么PMA的这种意外形状的问题
So now the question of this unexpected shape of these objects
在很长时间里我都没找到一个很好的答案
is something I've been trying to find a good answer to for a long time.
主要的问题是很多人给出的答案没有任何证据支持
The main problem is lots of people give answers which don't have any evidence to support it
而说实话 我的答案真的也没有一个好的来源
and truthfully I still don't really have a good source for my answer.
不过我可以排除一些网络上经常出现的不良理论
However I can rule out some bad theories that often turn up on internet.
首先 它不允许APAS的内部舱门进一步打开
Firstly it doesn't allow the interior hatch of the APAS to open further.
如果你看DM-2舱门打开的视频
If you watch the DM-2 hatch opening video,
你会得到很多视角显示舱门只折回了90度
you'll get lots of angles showing the hatch has been folded back only 90 degrees.
它不会一直折回墙边 因为铰链根本不允许
It doesn't fold all the way back against the wall because the hinges simply don't allow.
其次 它并没有增加航天飞机的安全系数
Secondly, it doesn't increase the safety margin for the space shuttle
所谓增加安全系数 是指最大限度地增加与航天飞机脆弱驾驶舱的距离
by maximizing the distance to the space shuttles fragile cabin.
当航天飞机对接时
when the space shuttle was docked,
它实际上是以一种最小化国际空间站舱段与驾驶舱距离的方式停靠的
it was actually docked in an orientation that minimized the distance to the cabin.
所以 最有可能的真相 其实是为了改善航天飞机货舱(有效载荷舱)的通道
So the most likely truth that is actually about improving access to this shuttles payload Bay.
当航天飞机使用对接系统的时候 对接口就在驾驶舱后方的货舱里
When the shuttle used the docking system, the docking port was in the payload bay just behind the cabin
而PMA的偏移量
and the offset in the pressurized mating adapter
可以让空间站相对航天飞机的位置靠前一点
removes the space shuttle backwards a little relative to the station
这样(从空间站)进入货舱的空间更大
and allows just a little bit more room to access the payload bay.
而且它还增加了一点移动机械臂的自由度
And it also adds a bit more freedom to move the manipulator arm
它的安装点确实靠近对接适配器
which has its mounting point really near the docking adaptor.
因此 这种特定的几何形状应该是让一些较大的元件
So the geometry had been carefully chosen to help give some of the larger components
像桁架段那种 在部署过程中得到更多的回旋余地
like the truss segments, get a bit more wiggle room during deployment.
当然对于站段之间的PMA来说 这是没有意义的
Of course this doesn't make sense for the PMA between the station segments
因为那里永远不会有航天飞机与之对接
because that would never have a shuttle docked to it.
事实上也不会有舱门
In fact also never had a hatch
但既然要建三个 就应该使用共同的设计
but since three were being built, it made sense to use a common design.
问题是整个空间站的对接系统的设计曾经发生了根本性的变化
The thing is the whole design of the docking system for the space station underwent a radical change
在俄罗斯开始介入时
when Russia started getting involved.
美国一直在开发自由号空间站
The US had been developing space station Freedom
我看过几张图片 显示出对接机制是明显不同的
and I've seen a few pictures showing the docking mechanism that looks significantly different.
我找不到任何参考资料来说明它是如何工作的
I can't find any reference as to how that worked.
我认为它把很多锚定结构放在空间站上了
I think it put a lot of the anchoring structure onto the space station
这样轨道器这边就不需要每次入轨都带上
so the orbiter didn't continually have to carry it to orbit.
实际上 它看起来有点像是从航天飞机上拆下来的对接适配器
And actually it looks somewhat similar to the docking adaptor when it's been taken out of the space shuttle.
所以 最终是航天飞机带上了大部分的结构
So what they ended up flying with had most of the structure on the space shuttle
也就是对接口和三个明显的对接瓣
with the docking port and the three alignment petals visible.
三瓣式设计来自于苏联研发的APAS-89标准
The three petal design comes from the APAS-89 standard which was developed by the Soviet Union.
他们想用它来实现暴风雪号航天飞机和和平号的对接
They wanted to use it to dock the Buran Space Shuttle to the Mir space station.
该设计有一个软捕获环 上面有三个金属瓣 用于软对接
The design has a soft capture ring with three metal petals for a soft alignment.
最初的捕获是用该环进行的
The initial capture is made with that ring
然后缩回并将两个航天器拉在一起 使硬捕获发生
which then retract and pulls the two spacecraft together to make the hard capture happen.
这其实和阿波罗-联盟号测试项目有一定的关系
And it's actually sorta related to the Apollo-Soyuz test project
他们用的是一个叫APAS-75的标准
which they used a standard called APAS-75.
而这也有三个对齐瓣
And that also had three alignment petals
但这种瓣是向外倾斜的 捕获环在加压系统的外部
but the petals were angled outwards and the capture ring was on the exterior of the pressure system.
在APAS-89中 花瓣和捕捉环移到了系统内部
With APAS-89 the petals and the ring moved to the inside
所以其实当你看空间站旅游视频的时候
so actually when you look at Space Station tour videos
你可以在这些通道里看到对接系统的瓣
you can see the petals from the docking system inside some of these tunnels.
所以和平号的这些对接口是为暴风雪号准备的
So Mir had these docking ports in anticipation of Buran
但暴风雪号并没有达到这一步
but Buran never made it that far.
他们确实开发出带有兼容性硬件的联盟号飞船 但这种飞船只进行过一次飞行
They did actually develop this Soyuz with compatible hardware but only one of those was ever flown.
开发这种飞船是为了开发出一种能从暴风雪号救援宇航员的方法
It was actually developed because they wanted a way to rescue cosmonauts from Buran
如果暴风雪号出现某种问题而不能返回地球时
if it had some sort of problem that left unable to return to Earth.
所以这艘飞船以联盟TM-16的代号在1993年飞往和平号 验证了新的对接系统
So this flew to Mir as Soyuz TM-16 in 1993 and demonstrated the new docking system.
常规的联盟号从来没有改用这个系统 因为这个装置明显重了很多
The regular Soyuz never switched over to this because the mechanism turned out to be significantly heavier
而这种改装会影响联盟号的运力
and the switch would have limited the capabilities
值得一提的是 TMA-16在发射时只有两名宇航员
and it's worth noting that TMA-16 only launched with two cosmonauts onboard.
但当它在和平号对接后 确实接了第三个人返回地球
But when it was in Mir, it did pick up a third for return to Earth.
那么 不管怎样 在同一时间 NASA正在寻找方法来合作 并研究
So anyway around the same time, NASA was looking for ways to cooperate and investigated
用联盟号作为自由号空间站的救生船的想法
the idea of using Soyuz as a lifeboat for this space station Freedom.
有一项研究是关于这个的
And there's a study for this
在其中 我看到了第一张现代PMA设计的渲染图 有了这个偏移
where that's when I see the first renderings of the modern PMA design with that offset.
同时航天飞机对接系统也转为APAS
At the same time the shuttle docking system also switched over to APAS
当然 这将使他们能够将航天飞机送到和平号上
and this will of course would enable them to send the space shuttle to Mir.
那么 他们确实对端口进行了一些设计和修改
Now they did remake some designs and revisions to the port.
在1995年成为新的标准 叫做APAS -95
It became as new standard called APAS-95 for 1995.
在最初的任务中 人们对对接的位置有所疑虑
Now for the original missions there were concerns about the location of where we dock
所以他们实际上移动了有对接口的晶体号实验舱
so they actually moved the Crystal module which had the docking port
把它移到一个新的位置 以确保航天飞机有适当的空间
into a new location to make sure the space shuttle had the correct clearances
但在第三次访问和平号的航天飞机任务STS-74中
but on the third space shuttle mission to visit Mir, STS-74,
他们带来了一个特殊的扩展模块 可以把对接口移到离空间站更远的地方
they brought along a special extension module that would move the docking port further away from the station.
Chris Hatfield是那个在国际空间站出MV(b23.tv/av667616649)的加拿大宇航员，2013年退役
这实际上是Chris Hatfield的第一次飞行
This was actually a Chris Hatfield's first flight.
那么说白了 这个对接适配器两边都有APAS端口
So this docking adaptor basically had APAS ports on both sides
而它实际上是由联盟号飞船的轨道舱制成的
and it was actually made of orbit modules from Soyuz spacecraft
中间多了一个圆柱形的支架
with an extra cylindrical sanction in the middle.
只是把这些东西背对背地焊接起来 这样就把对接系统移到了离空间站足够远的地方
They just welded those back-to-back and it moved the docking system far enough away from the station
这样就不必为了航天飞机而不断移动晶体号实验舱了
that they didn't have to keep moving the Crystal module around for the space shuttle.
所以同样的对接系统也被用于对接国际空间站
And so the same docking system was used for docking to the International Space Station
虽然一个值得注意的区别是
Although one noteworthy difference is that
当他们与和平号对接时 对接系统被放置在航天飞机货舱较后面的位置
the docking system is placed further back in the shuttle bay when they were docking with Mir.
而去国际空间站对接的时候 它被移到了更靠前的位置 就在驾驶舱的后面
When they were going to the International Space Station, it was moved right up against the back of the cabin.
当然那是因为他们需要进入货舱
And that was because of course they needed access to the payload bay
而货舱要为所有被运送到空间站的部件留出空间
for all the parts that were being delivered to the space station.
所以如果你仔细想想
And so if you think about it.
尽管暴风雪号在很多方面是航天飞机的复制品
The Buran was in many ways a copy of the space shuttle.
但最终航天飞机为了对接和平号而使用了为暴风雪号设计的对接系统
But in the end the space shuttle used the docking system designed for a Buran as its docking system.
还有就是宇航员必须要经过的通道中的那个弯道
And also that kink in the tunnel that the astronauts have to go through
当他们从龙飞船或星际客机上下来时 有可能会撞到他们的头
when they're getting out of Dragon or Starliner and risk banging their heads.
那是因为航天飞机的遗留决策
That is because of legacy decisions for the space shuttle.
而我认为偶尔撞撞头总比换掉一大堆设备要好
And I'll take more than the occasional bumped head to justify changing out such a large chunk of hardware.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
[音乐]
[Music]